Guide to the photograph album Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman AD.MC.046
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman
1936-1938
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Voyager Press. Rare Books and Manuscripts
AD.MC.046
42 Photographic Prints Oblong 8vo. string­tied album, brown cloth snake­skinned styled boards with green cloth spine, measuring approximately 32 x 22 x 3,5 cm. Contains 42 large format gelatin silver print photographs, mounted with corners onto brown cardstock leaves, meticulously captioned and ruled in manuscript, with the exception of four which are loosely placed within the volume. Photographs measure approximately 22 x 16 cm, with only slight variation. Some wear to boards, otherwise in Very Good Condition.
Album of large format photographs, featuring rare and stellar views of Kurdistan and Baghdad, part of what was then the Kingdom of Iraq, taken by an RAF officer while serving with the AHQ Iraq Command (same handwriting as Iraq, Egypt, Yemen - compiled by L. Wells album in Hisham Khatib Collection AD_MC_030_ref158) between 1936-1938. The album also contains views of RAF Camp "Ser Amadia" which was a summer training camp in the northern mountains of Iraq in Kurdistan. [The first reference to this camp is found in the Foreign Office files of 1931, only six years prior to these views, indicating it had been in use in 1930. The camp was set up in April each year and closed in September. There were two adjacent sections, a Levy camp and a British camp for those on leave. The levies provided the local guard and security for those on leave. The officer was sent to Egypt in 1938, after his service in Mesopotamia, retaining in this album photographs of two manicured gardens in Alexandria (Nuzha and Antoniadis) and two of the squadron to which he was assigned in Aboukir [Abu Qir].
Graphics AD_MC_046
Content Description
Album of large format photographs, featuring rare and stellar views of Kurdistan and Baghdad, part of what was then the Kingdom of Iraq, taken by an RAF officer while serving abroad with the AHQ Iraq Command (same handwriting as album in Hisham Khatib Collection AD_MC_030_ref158).
Biographical / Historical
Text from the description by Voyager Press: "A rare glimpse into the lives of Assyrians and Kurds in Mesopotamia, as well as beautiful views of Baghdad which had then just recently, in 1932, become the capital of the Kingdom of Iraq.
In Kurdistan, nostalgic views show an Assyrian village called Haisi [more recently known as Haisse], the lovely alpine village Sulav, and also the Kurdish town of Amadia [Amadiya], the latter being an ancient mountain top village and Hill station situated along a tributary to the Great Zab river in the Dahuk Governorate of Iraqi Kurdistan, a town which has become a popular summer resort.
Striking views of Baghdad render the most pleasing scenes of exquisite architecture, ancient partially excavated ruins, horse­drawn carriages travelling city streets, an outdoor Iraqi haikhana [teahouse], a fruit market.
Fascinated by the people, he captures excellent snapshot photographs of vibrant personalities. Others include an aged savant, a Bedouin woman and her children, an Assyrian farmer with his cattle, a nomad or merchant on a camel, and an ominous scene of a somber woman with child carrying a small locking chest on her head.
The album also contains views of RAF Camp "Ser Amadia" which was a summer training camp in the northern mountains of Iraq in Kurdistan. [The first reference to this camp is found in the Foreign Office files of 1931, only six years prior to these views, indicating it had been in use in 1930. The camp was set up in April each year and closed in September. There were two adjacent sections, a Levy camp and a British camp for those on leave. The last summer season was in 1954 as the camp could not reopen after the Levies were disbanded in May 1955. The levies provided the local guard and security for those on leave.] The officer was sent to Egypt in 1938, after his service in Mesopotamia, retaining in this album photographs of two manicured gardens in Alexandria (Nuzha and Antoniadis) and two of the squadron to which he was assigned in Aboukir [Abu Qir]. One of these group photographs is captioned to verso, "A Sqdn. Aboukir 1938. CO W/Cdr D. Daith." An earlier group photograph of 14 men with lacrosse sticks suggests a leave, with its caption, "A Workshop Squadron. RAF Depot ME. Aboukir. A.S.L. Winners 1936­37."
Iraq; Southern Kurdistan, Iraq; Military/Soldiers; Architecture; Royal Air Force; Voyager Press. Rare Books and Manuscripts
- The front cover of the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref1; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Iraq; Royal Air Force
- The inside front cover of the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref2; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- An aerial view of an RAF military base, most likely in Iraq (linked Ref38)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref3; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Iraq; Royal Air Force; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Palm Trees; Military/Soldiers
- A view of 'Paradise Valley' in Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref4; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; English Writing; Landscapes; Mountains/Hills; Iraq; Outdoors; Countryside/Rural
- A view of mountains and a valley in Haisi (Haisse)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref5; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Landscapes; Mountains/Hills; Iraq; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; English Writing; Outdoors; Countryside/Rural
- The Ser Amadia (Amadiya/Amedi) Gorge., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref6; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Landscapes; Amadiya/Amedi, Kurdistan, Iraq; Outdoors; Countryside/Rural; English Writing; Mountains/Hills
- A view of buildings, captioned "Assyrian dwelling", with two children in the background, in Haisi (Haisse)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref7; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; English Writing; Buildings; Countryside/Rural; Children; Iraq
- A view of people on a road in Sulav., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref8; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Streets/Roads; Children; Buildings; Countryside/Rural; English Writing; Mountains/Hills; Men; Regional/National Dress; Sulav, Kurdistan, Iraq
- The village of Amadia (Amadiya), including a view of the Great Mosque of Amadiya., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref9; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Amadiya/Amedi, Kurdistan, Iraq; Mosques; Landscapes; Buildings; Architecture; Countryside/Rural; English Writing; Mountains/Hills
- A portrait of a man with livestock entitled "Assyrian Farming.", Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref10; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Regional/National Dress; Men; Agriculture/Farms; Mountains/Hills; Individual Portraits; Cattle/Cows; Animals; Countryside/Rural; Donkeys; Southern Kurdistan, Iraq; English Writing
- A mountainside and building in Sulav., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref11; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Countryside/Rural; Mountains/Hills; Sulav, Kurdistan, Iraq; English Writing
- An aerial view of the RAF summer training camp at Ser Amadia (Ser Amadiya)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref12; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Landscapes; Tents; Royal Air Force; Mountains/Hills; Streets/Roads; Military/Soldiers; Amadiya/Amedi, Kurdistan, Iraq; English Writing
- A view of tents at the RAF summer training camp at Ser Amadia (Ser Amadiya)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref13; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Amadiya/Amedi, Kurdistan, Iraq; Tents; Royal Air Force; Military/Soldiers; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; English Writing; Flags
- A group portrait of nine children, captioned "Assyrian children.", Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref14; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boys; Girls; Children; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Hats; Countryside/Rural; Southern Kurdistan, Iraq; English Writing
- A landscape of the mountains surrounding the River Zab, including a view of a bridge., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref15; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Great Zab River; Bridges; Mountains/Hills; Water; Rivers; Landscapes; Countryside/Rural; Southern Kurdistan, Iraq; English Writing
- A group portrait of children, men, and women sitting under a structure, captioned "Assyrian Koprana"., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref16; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Group Portraits; Boys; Girls; Children; Women; Men; Restaurants/bars; Regional/National Dress; Southern Kurdistan, Iraq
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref17; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A view of the ruins of Babylon., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref18; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Landscapes; Hillah/al-Ḥillah, Iraq; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Buildings; Palm Trees; English Writing
- A view of the 'processional way to the Temple of Marduk.' (Amran Ibn Ali) in Babylon, Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref19; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Temples; Hillah/al-Ḥillah, Iraq; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Buildings; Architecture; Palm Trees; English Writing
- A landscape of the Hillah branch of the Euphrates River., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref20; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Landscapes; Rivers; Water; Palm Trees; Hillah/al-Ḥillah, Iraq; Euphrates River; English Writing
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref21; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A street scene in Baghdad, Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref22; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; English Writing; Mosques; Buildings; Architecture; Streets/Roads; Women; Regional/National Dress; Men; Head Covers/Veils; Cars/Trucks; Carriages/Coaches; Religious Sites; Baghdad, Iraq; Transportation
- A view of the Blue Mosque (Haydar-Khana Mosque) in Baghdad, Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref23; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Streets/Roads; Religious Sites; Carriages/Coaches; Horses; Animals; Shops; Men; Women; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Children; Baghdad, Iraq; English Writing; Transportation
- A portrait of men sitting at a tea house in Baghdad, Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref24; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Regional/National Dress; Group Portraits; Restaurants/bars; Facial Hair; Fez/Tarboush; Smoking; Tea/Coffee; Buildings; Electricity; Palm Trees; English Writing; Baghdad, Iraq; Cigarettes; Furnishings
- People standing in front of a fruit shop in Baghdad, Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref25; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Shops; Workers; Men; Regional/National Dress; Children; Girls; Fez/Tarboush; Head Covers/Veils; Boys; Women; Food; Baghdad, Iraq; English Writing
- A portrait of a woman holding a child and carrying a BP oil cannister on her head., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref26; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Group Portraits; Children; Petroleum industry and trade.; Streets/Roads; Iraq
- A portrait of a bearded man, captioned "By the beard of the Prophet."., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref27; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Facial Hair; Regional/National Dress; Men; Individual Portraits; Iraq; English Writing
- A portrait of four children, captioned "Bedouins"., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref28; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Girls; Children; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Jewelry; English Writing; Iraq
- A portrait of a woman named Selima (linked ref158_000007, AD_MC_044_ref20)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref29; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Women; Workers; Food; Children; English Writing; Iraq
- A portrait of two men; one riding a camel, the other standing beside it., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref30; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Group Portraits; Camels; Animals; Regional/National Dress; Facial Hair; Palm Trees; Deserts; English Writing; Iraq; Military/Soldiers; Uniforms
- A view of boats beached on a shoreline., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref31; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Landscapes; Beaches; Water; Alexandria, Egypt
- A view of the Antoniadis Garden in Alexandria, Egypt., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref32; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Gardens; Parks; Statues/Sculptures; Landscapes; Alexandria, Egypt
- A view of the El Nozha Garden in Alexandria, Egypt., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref33; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Gardens; Parks; Palm Trees; Alexandria, Egypt; Landscapes
- A view of a ship (linked ref35)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref34; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boats/Ships; Water; Landscapes; Mountains/Hills; Transportation; Military/Soldiers; Unknown Locations; Airplanes; Royal Air Force
- A view of a ship (linked ref34)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref35; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boats/Ships; Water; Transportation; Airplanes; Unknown Locations; Military/Soldiers; Royal Air Force
- A view of a military ship., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref36; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Military/Soldiers; Water; Buildings; Flags; Ports; Guns; Weapons; Airplanes; Unknown Locations
- A group portrait of RAF personnel., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref37; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Military/Soldiers; Uniforms; Royal Air Force; Medals/Insignia; Hats; Group Portraits; Men; Unknown Locations; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Facial Hair; Gloves
- An aerial view of an RAF military base, most likely in Iraq (linked Ref3)., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref38; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Royal Air Force; Iraq; Landscapes; Deserts; Streets/Roads; Palm Trees; Buildings; Military/Soldiers
- A view of biplanes in an airfield, most likely in Iraq., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref39; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Airplanes; Airports; Transportation; Military/Soldiers; Royal Air Force; Buildings; Iraq; Royal Air Force
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref40; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A group portrait of RAF personnel holding hockey sticks, including Les Wells on the right in the front row., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref41; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Royal Air Force; Military/Soldiers; Sports; Uniforms; Medals/Insignia; Men; Hats; Group Portraits; Women; Iraq
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref42; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A group portrait of several men and children posed in front of an airplane., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref43; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Group Portraits; Men; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Children; Airplanes; Military/Soldiers; Boys; Deserts; Iraq; Transportation; Royal Air Force
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref44; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A street scene in Baghdad, including a shop advertising His Master's Voice gramophones and the Haydar-Khana Mosque., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref45; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Mosques; Religious Sites; Buildings; Architecture; Bicycles/Tricycles; Transportation; Fez/Tarboush; Men; Streets/Roads; Shops; Signs/Signposts; Dogs; Animals; Women; Children; Electricity; Arabic Writing; Baghdad, Iraq; Carriages/Coaches
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref46; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A group portrait of four children playing musical instruments, including a banjo, trumpet, and ukulele., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref47; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Musical Instruments; Brass Instruments; String Instruments; Boys; Girls; Children; Group Portraits; Unknown Locations
- A blank page in the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref48; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
- A signed portrait of Les Wells posing at a piano (linked to ref158_000039 in album 'Iraq, Egypt, Yemen - compiled by L. Wells - Hisham Khatib Collection' and AD_MC_044_ref44 in 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by L. Wells of RAF Hinaidi')., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref49; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Pianos; Musical Instruments; Men; Royal Air Force; Military/Soldiers; Tuxedos; Performing Arts; Individual Portraits; Signatures; Bow Ties; Unknown Locations
- A view of the Gateway of India in Mumbai., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref50; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Architecture; Mumbai/Bombay, India; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Streets/Roads; Street Lamps; Men
- A sunset over a body of water., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref51; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)
  Iraq; Palm Trees; Photographic Prints; Rivers; Water; Landscapes; Gelatin Silver Prints
- The back cover of the album 'Iraq and Kurdistan - compiled by an RAF serviceman'., Circa 1936-1938; AD_MC_046_ref52; Wells, Les, Active 1929 - 1939; 1 Photographic Prints (Graphics AD_MC_046)